the then Vice President of the United States, Mr. Al Gore. And I did what every single teenage girl would want to do. I wanted to somehow express all of this love, so I built him a website, it's over here. And in 2001, there was no Tumblr, there was no Facebook, there was no Pinterest. So I needed to learn to code in order to express all of this longing and loving. And that is how programming started for me. It started as a means of self-expression. Just like when I was smaller, I would use crayons and legos. And when I was older, I would use guitar lessons and theater plays. But then, there were other things to get excited about, like poetry and knitting socks and conjugating French irregular verbs and coming up with make-believe worlds and Bertrand Russell and his philosophy. And I started to be one of those people who felt that computers are boring and technical and lonely. Here's what I think today. Little girls don't know that they are not supposed to like computers. Little girls are amazing. They are really, really good at concentrating on things and being exact and they ask amazing questions like, "What?" and "Why?" and "How?" and "What if?" And they don't know that they are not supposed to like computers. It's the parents who do. It's us parents who feel like computer science is this esoteric, weird science discipline that only belongs to the mystery makers. That it's almost as far removed from everyday life as, say, nuclear physics. And they are partly right about that. There's a lot of syntax and controls and data structures and algorithms and practices, protocols and paradigms in programming. And we as a community, we've made computers smaller and smaller. We've built layers and layers of abstraction on top of each other between the man and the machine to the point that we no longer have any idea how computers work or how to talk to them. And we do teach our kids how the human body works, we teach them how the combustion engine functions and we even tell them that if you want to really be an astronaut you can become one. But when the kid comes to us and asks, "So, what is a bubble sort algorithm?" Or, "How does the computer know what happens when I press 'play,' how does it know which video to show?"
el vicepresidente de EE.UU., el Sr. Al Gore. E hice lo que toda adolescente quisiera hacer. Quería en cierto modo expresar todo este amor, así que le hice un sitio web, está por aquí. En 2001, no había Tumblr, no había Facebook, no había Pinterest. Por eso tuve que aprender a programar para expresar esas ansias y ese amor. Así empecé a programar. Primero como medio de autoexpresión. De la misma forma que de pequeña usaba crayones y legos. De más mayor, usaba clases de guitarra y obras de teatro. Pero luego, me apasioné por otras cosas, como la poesía, el tejido de calcetines, la conjugación de verbos irregulares en francés, la invención de mundos imaginarios, Bertrand Russell y su filosofía. Y empecé a ser de esas personas que sentían que las computadoras eran aburridas, técnicas y solitarias. Hoy pienso de esta manera: Las niñitas no saben que no deberían gustarles las computadoras. Las niñitas son increíbles. Son muy, muy buenas para concentrarse en cosas, ser exactas y hacerse preguntas increíbles como: "¿Qué?", "¿Por qué?", "¿Cómo? y "¿Qué tal si?" Y no saben que se supone que no deberían gustarles las computadoras. Son los padres quienes lo piensan. Los padres sí sentimos que la informática es una disciplina esotérica, una ciencia extraña, que solo pertenece a hacedores misteriosos; que está tan disociada de la vida cotidiana como, digamos, la física nuclear. Y eso tiene parte de razón. Hay mucha sintaxis, controles, estructuras de datos, algoritmos, prácticas, protocolos y paradigmas en la programación. Y, como comunidad, hicimos computadoras cada vez más pequeñas. Construimos capas y capas de abstracción unas sobre otras entre el humano y la máquina hasta el punto de no tener idea de cómo funcionan las computadoras, o cómo hablarles. Y enseñamos a nuestros niños cómo funciona el cuerpo humano, les enseñamos cómo funcionan los motores de combustión e incluso les decimos que si realmente quieren ser astronautas pueden llegar a serlo. Pero cuando el niño viene y pregunta: "¿Qué es un algoritmo de ordenamiento de burbuja?" ¿Cómo sabe la computadora qué sucede cuando presiono "reproducir"? ¿Cómo sabe qué video mostrar?
Or, "Linda, is Internet a place?" We adults, we grow oddly silent. "It's magic," some of us say. "It's too complicated," the others say. Well, it's neither. It's not magic and it's not complicated. It all just happened really, really, really fast. Computer scientists built these amazing, beautiful machines, but they made them very, very foreign to us, and also the language we speak to the computers so that we don't know how to speak to the computers anymore without our fancy user interfaces. And that's why no one recognized that when I was conjugating French irregular verbs, I was actually practicing my pattern recognition skills. And when I was excited about knitting, I actually was following a sequence of symbolic commands that included loops inside of them. And that Bertrand Russell's lifelong quest to find an exact language between English and mathematics found its home inside of a computer. I was a programmer, but no one knew it. The kids of today, they tap, swipe and pinch their way through the world. But unless we give them tools to build with computers, we are raising only consumers instead of creators. This whole quest led me to this little girl. Her name is Ruby, she is six years old. She is completely fearless, imaginative and a little bit bossy. And every time I would run into a problem in trying to teach myself programming like, "What is object-oriented design or what is garbage collection?", I would try to imagine how a six-year-old little girl would explain the problem. And I wrote a book about her and I illustrated it and the things Ruby taught me go like this. Ruby taught me that you're not supposed to be afraid of the bugs under your bed. And even the biggest of the problems are a group of tiny problems stuck together. And Ruby also introduced me to her friends, the colorful side of the Internet culture. She has friends like the Snow Leopard, who is beautiful but doesn't want to play with the other kids. And she has friends like the green robots that are really friendly but super messy. And she has friends like Linux the penguin who's really ruthlessly efficient, but somewhat hard to understand. And idealistic foxes, and so on. In Ruby's world, you learn technology through play. And, for instance, computers are really good at repeating stuff, so the way Ruby would teach loops goes like this. This is Ruby's favorite dance move, it goes, "Clap, clap, stomp, stomp clap, clap and jump." And you learn counter loops by repeating that four times. And you learn while loops by repeating that sequence while I'm standing on one leg. And you learn until loops by repeating that sequence until mom gets really mad. (Laughter) And most of all, you learn that there are no ready answers. When coming up with the curriculum for Ruby's world, I needed to really ask the kids how they see the world and what kind of questions they have and I would organize play testing sessions. I would start by showing the kids these four pictures. I would show them a picture of a car, a grocery store, a dog and a toilet. And I would ask, "Which one of these do you think is a computer?" And the kids would be very conservative and go, "None of these is a computer. I know what a computer is: it's that glowing box in front of which mom or dad spends way too much time." But then we would talk and we would discover that actually, a car is a computer, it has a navigation system inside of it. And a dog -- a dog might not be a computer, but it has a collar and the collar might have a computer inside of it. And grocery stores, they have so many different kinds of computers, like the cashier system and the burglar alarms. And kids, you know what? In Japan, toilets are computers
Linda, ¿Internet es un lugar?" Los adultos nos quedamos en un silencio extraño. "Es magia", dicen unos. "Es muy complicado", dicen otros. Bueno, ninguna de las dos. No es magia ni es complicado. Sencillamente ocurre muy, muy, muy rápido. Los informáticos construyen hermosas máquinas increíbles, pero las hacen tan, tan ajenas a nosotros, y también al lenguaje con el que hablamos con las computadoras que ya no sabemos cómo hablar a las máquinas sin nuestras interfaces elaboradas. Y por eso nadie reconocía que cuando yo conjugaba verbos irregulares en francés, en realidad practicaba reconocimiento de patrones. Y cuando me apasionaba tejiendo, en realidad seguía una secuencia de comandos simbólicos que tenía bucles. Y que la eterna búsqueda de Bertrand Russell por encontrar un lenguaje exacto entre el inglés y las matemáticas encontró su lugar dentro de la computadora. Yo era programadora, pero nadie lo sabía. Los niños de hoy tocan, deslizan, y pulsan su camino hacia el mundo. Pero si no les damos herramientas para construir con computadoras, solo creamos consumidores en vez de creadores. Toda esta búsqueda me llevó a esta niña. Su nombre es Ruby, tiene seis años. No tiene miedo, tiene imaginación, y es un poco mandona. Y cada vez que encontraba un problema como autodidacta de la programación, preguntaba: "¿Qué es el diseño orientado a objetos o qué es la recolección de residuos?" Trataba de imaginar cómo explicaría el problema una niña de seis años. Y escribí un libro sobre ella y lo ilustré y Ruby me enseñó estas cosas. Me enseñó que no se debe tener miedo a los "bugs" bajo la cama. Y que hasta el mayor de los problemas es un grupo de pequeños problemas apilados. Y Ruby me presentó a sus amigas, el lado colorido de la cultura de Internet. Ella tiene amigos como el leopardo de las nieves, que es hermoso, pero no quiere jugar con otros niños. Tiene amigos como los robots verdes muy amigables, pero súper desordenados. Y tiene amigos como Linux el pingüino implacablemente eficiente, pero un poco difícil de entender. Y zorros idealistas, etc. En el mundo de Ruby, uno aprende tecnología mediante el juego. Y, por ejemplo, las computadoras son muy buenas para repetir cosas, entonces Ruby enseña bucles así. El paso de baile favorito de Ruby, es: "Palma, palma, pisa, pisa, palma, palma y salto". Y uno aprende bucles "contadores" repitiendo eso cuatro veces. Y aprende bucles de tipo "mientras" repitiendo esa secuencia mientras me paro en un pie. Y aprende bucles de tipo "hasta" repitiendo esa secuencia hasta que mamá se enoje. (Risas) Y, sobre todo, se aprende que no hay respuestas inmediatas. Cuando ideaba el plan del mundo de Ruby, precisaba preguntarle a los niños cómo ven el mundo y qué tipo de preguntas tienen, y organizaba sesiones lúdicas experimentales. Empezaba mostrando a los niños estas cuatro imágenes. Les mostraba la imagen de un auto, una tienda de comestibles, un perro y un sanitario. Y preguntaba: "¿Cuál piensas que es una computadora?" Los niños eran muy conservadores y decían: "Ninguna es una computadora. Yo sé lo que es una computadora: es esa caja brillante con la que papá y mamá pasan mucho tiempo". Pero luego hablábamos y descubríamos que en realidad un auto es una computadora, pues tiene un sistema de navegación. Y un perro no puede ser una computadora, pero tiene un collar y el collar puede tener una computadora dentro. Y la tienda de comestibles tiene muchos tipos de computadoras, como el sistema del cajero y las alarmas antirrobo. Y los niños, ¿saben qué? En Japón, los sanitarios son computadoras
and there's even hackers who hack them. (Laughter) And we go further and I give them these little stickers with an on/off button on them. And I tell the kids, "Today you have this magic ability to make anything in this room into a computer." And again, the kids go, "Sounds really hard, I don't know the right answer for this." But I tell them, "Don't worry, your parents don't know the right answer, either. They've just started to hear about this thing called The Internet of Things. But you kids, you are going to be the ones who are really going to live up in a world where everything is a computer." And then I had this little girl who came to me and took a bicycle lamp and she said, "This bicycle lamp, if it were a computer, it would change colors." And I said, "That's a really good idea, what else could it do?" And she thinks and she thinks, and she goes, "If this bicycle lamp were a computer, we could go on a biking trip with my father and we would sleep in a tent and this biking lamp could also be a movie projector." And that's the moment I'm looking for, the moment when the kid realizes that the world is definitely not ready yet, that a really awesome way of making the world more ready is by building technology and that each one of us can be a part of that change. Final story, we also built a computer. And we got to know the bossy CPU and the helpful RAM and ROM that help it remember things. And after we've assembled our computer together, we also design an application for it. And my favorite story is this little boy, he's six years old and his favorite thing in the world is to be an astronaut. And the boy, he has these huge headphones on and he's completely immersed in his tiny paper computer because you see, he's built his own intergalactic planetary navigation application. And his father, the lone astronaut in the Martian orbit, is on the other side of the room and the boy's important mission is to bring the father safely back to earth. And these kids are going to have a profoundly different view of the world and the way we build it with technology. Finally, the more approachable, the more inclusive, and the more diverse we make the world of technology, the more colorful and better the world will look like. So, imagine with me, for a moment, a world where the stories we tell about how things get made don't only include the twentysomething-year-old Silicon Valley boys, but also Kenyan schoolgirls and Norwegian librarians. Imagine a world where the little Ada Lovelaces of tomorrow, who live in a permanent reality of 1s and 0s, they grow up to be very optimistic and brave about technology. They embrace the powers and the opportunities and the limitations of the world. A world of technology that is wonderful, whimsical and a tiny bit weird. When I was a girl, I wanted to be a storyteller. I loved make-believe worlds and my favorite thing to do was to wake up in the mornings in Moominvalley.
e incluso son atacados por "hackers". (Risas) Vamos más lejos y les doy uno de esos adhesivos que tienen botones encendido/apagado. Y le dije a los niños: "Hoy tienen el poder mágico para transformar cualquier cosa en una computadora". Y, nuevamente, los niños decían: "Parece difícil, no sé la respuesta correcta". Pero les digo: "No se preocupen, sus padres tampoco conocen la respuesta correcta. Apenas conocen algo llamado Internet de las Cosas. Pero Uds. niños, serán quienes vivirán realmente en un mundo en el que todo será una computadora". Y luego se me acercó una niñita, tomó la lámpara de una bici y dijo: "Si esta lámpara fuera una computadora, cambiaría de colores". Y yo dije: "Es una idea muy buena, ¿qué otra cosa podría hacer?" Ella piensa y piensa, y dice: "Si esta lámpara de bicicleta fuera una computadora, podríamos hacer un viaje en bicicleta con papá, dormiríamos en una tienda, y esta lámpara de bicicleta también podría ser un proyector de películas". Y busco ese momento, en que el niño se da cuenta de que el mundo definitivamente no es algo terminado, que una manera increíble de completarlo es creando tecnología y que cada uno de nosotros puede ser parte de ese cambio. Última historia, también construimos una computadora. Conocimos a la CPU mandona y a las útiles memorias RAM y ROM que ayudan a recordar cosas. Después de montar la computadora, también diseñamos una aplicación. Y mi historia favorita es la de este niñito, tiene seis años y su cosa favorita en el mundo es ser astronauta. El niño tiene esos auriculares enormes y está completamente inmerso en su pequeña computadora de papel porque vean, construyó su propia aplicación de navegación planetaria intergaláctica. Y su padre, el astronauta solitario en la órbita marciana, está al otro lado de la sala y la misión importante del niño consiste en traer a su padre a salvo de vuelta a la Tierra. Estos niños tendrán una visión profundamente diferente del mundo y de la manera de construirlo con tecnología. Por último, cuanto más accesible, más inclusivo, y diverso hagamos el mundo de la tecnología, mejor y más colorido será el mundo. Por eso, imaginemos juntos, por un momento, un mundo en el que las historias que contamos sobre cómo se hacen las cosas no solo convoquen a veinteañeros de Silicon Valley, sino también a colegialas kenianas y a bibliotecarios noruegos. Imaginen un mundo en el que la pequeña Ada Lovelaces del mañana, que viven en una realidad permanente de unos y ceros, crezcan optimistas y valientes respecto de la tecnología. Ellas aceptan los poderes, las oportunidades y las limitaciones del mundo. Un mundo de tecnologías encantadoras, extravagantes, y un poquito extrañas. De niña, quería ser narradora. Me encantaban los mundos imaginarios; mi situación favorita era despertar por la mañana en Moominvalley,
In the afternoons, I would roam around the Tatooines. And in the evenings, I would go to sleep in Narnia. And programming turned out to be the perfect profession for me. I still create worlds. Instead of stories, I do them with code. Programming gives me this amazing power to build my whole little universe with its own rules and paradigms and practices. Create something out of nothing with the pure power of logic. Thank you. (Applause)
vagar por la tarde en Tatooines e ir a dormir por la noche a Narnia. La programación terminó siendo mi profesión ideal. Todavía creo mundos. En vez de historias, los hago con código. La programación me da ese poder increíble para construir mi pequeño universo con sus propias reglas, paradigmas y prácticas. Para crear algo de la nada con el poder puro de la lógica. Gracias. (Aplausos)